Dr. Steven R. Goldman

Software Engineer · Space Telescope Science Institute 3700 San Martin Drive Baltimore, MD 21218 sgoldman@stsci.edu

Research Interests: The effects of metallicity on the dust production, wind dynamics, mass-loss mechanism, and evolution of Asymptotic Giant Branch stars and Red Supergiants.

APPOINTMENTS

| Software Engineer II, STScI | February 2023 - present |
|--|-------------------------------|
| Visiting Assistant Professor, Haverford College, PA | January 2023 - present |
| Observatory & Instrument Scientist, SOFIA | November 2021 - February 2023 |
| Postdoctoral Fellow, Space Telescope Science Institute | October 2017 - November 2021 |

EDUCATION

PhD in Astrophysics Keele University, UK

October 2013 - December 2017

- o Advisor: Jacco Th. van Loon
- Thesis: The metallicity dependence of maser emission and mass loss from red supergiants and asymptotic giant branch stars
- B. S. in Physics St. Lawrence University, USA

September 2009 - July 2013

AWARDED PROPOSALS (PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR)

| 2022 Hubble Space Telescope, PID: 17088 (\$137 k) | 30 primary orbits |
|--|---------------------|
| 2022 SOFIA (first quintile) | 18 hours (canceled) |
| 2022 GASKAP-OH (Science team lead: LMC maser populations | s) 50 hours |
| 2021 Hubble Space Telescope, PID: 16492 (\$65 k) | 4 primary orbits |
| 2021 SOFIA, PID: 75_0057 (\$40 k) | 4 hours |
| 2017 Australia Telescope Compact Array Telescope, PID: C2996 | 92 hours |
| 2017 Very Large Telescope VISIR, PID: 099.D-0907 | 1 Night |
| 2017 Very Large Telescope VISIR, PID: 098.D-0272 | 0.5 hours |
| 2016 Very Large Telescope XSHOOTER, PID: 097.D-0605 | 1.5 hours |
| 2015 Westerbork Synthesis Radio Telescope, PID: R14/010 | 30 hours |
| 2014 Southern African Large Telescope | 5.5 hours |

RECENT AWARDED PROPOSALS (CO-INVESTIGATOR)

| James Webb Space Telescope (2 programs) | 60 primary / 2 parallel orbits |
|--|-----------------------------------|
| Hubble Space Telescope (7 programs) | 102 primary / 520 parallel orbits |
| SOFIA (2 programs) | 20.25 hours |
| SOFIA Legacy (cut short by cancellation) | 100 hours \rightarrow 4 hours |
| ACA (NESS) | 750 hours |
| Astrophysics Data Analysis Program (18-ADA | AP18-142) \$335 k |
| ALMA | 5 hours |

SELECTED SEMINAR & CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

| 2022 Invited Speaker, IAU General Assembly | Busan, South Korea |
|--|--|
| 2022 Featured Speaker, AstroPhilly22 | Villanova University, USA |
| 2022 Invited Colloquim | University of Auckland, New Zealand |
| 2022 Invited Colloquim | Auckland University of Technology, New Zealand |
| 2022 Invited Colloquim | University of Canterbury, New Zealand |
| 2022 Invited Talk, AAS Summer Meeting | Pasadena, USA |
| 2022 Invited Colloquim | NRC Herzberg, Canada |
| 2022 Poster, SOFIA Lake Arrowhead Conferen | ce, CA, USA |
| 2021 Invited Panelist, Evolved Stars and their | Circumstellar Environments Global (Remote) |
| 2021 Invited Talk, GAPS: unsolved problems i | n red Giants And suPergiantS Global (Remote) |
| 2021 Talk, DELVE: The Death-Throes of Evol | ed Stars Global (Remote) |
| 2021 Invited Talk | St. Lawrence University, USA |
| 2020 Invited Talk | STScI, USA |
| 2020 Poster, AAS Winter Meeting | Honolulu, USA |
| 2019 Invited Colloquim | RIT, USA |
| 2019 Invited Colloquim | EAO Hawaii, USA |
| 2019 Talk, A Star Has Evolved: A Conference | 9 , |
| 2019 Talk, HotSci | STScI, USA |
| 2019 Poster, AAS Winter Meeting | Seattle, USA |
| 2018 Poster, IAU General Assembly | Vienna, Austria |
| 2018 Talk, Cosmic Dust: origin, applications & | |
| 2018 Talk, European Week in Astronomy and | |
| 2016 Talk, Blowing in the wind (Awarded Best | |
| 2016 Talk, Postgraduate Research Symposium | |
| 2016 Talk, SKA Delivering the Science | Cambridge University, UK |
| 2015 Talk, UK SKA Science Meeting | Manchester University, UK |
| 2015 Poster, Stellar End Products: The low m | |
| 2015 Invited Colloquim, | Kagoshima University, Japan |

MENTORING, TEACHING, & OUTREACH

Students Mentored:

2022 S. Garner, USRA Intern, SOFIA/EXES Water Line Analysis of the Symbiotic Mira HM Sge 2022 N. Wolthuis, USRA Intern, HST/WFC3 Image Analysis of Nebular NII emission of HM Sge

Courses:

Visiting Assistant Professor, Astro 101, Haverford College, (Spring 2023) Demonstrator/Lab Assistant, Electronics, Keele University (2014-2016) Demonstrator/Lab Assistant, Programming I, Keele University (2015)

Virtual Community Outreach, 2018 – Present, (USA, Canada, & Mexico)

- \circ Skype-a-Scientist
- NASA's Universe of Learning
- Independently organized

Earth and Space Observatory volunteer, 2013–2017, (Keele University, UK)

OBSERVING EXPERIENCE

| SOFIA | 3 flights |
|-----------------------------------|-----------|
| James Clerk Maxwell Telescope | 70 hours |
| Very Large Telescope | 1 night |
| Australia Telescope Compact Array | 92 hours |
| Parkes Radio Telescope | 36 hours |
| Arecibo L-band (ALFALFA) | 20 hours |

SELECTED TECHNICAL/FUNCTIONAL ACHIEVEMENTS

Tools for Increasing Scientific Productivity

(Independently Created, Developed, & Maintained)

- SOFIA Data-Analysis Cookbooks: Jupyter notebooks demonstrating a variety of techniques for analyzing infrared data from SOFIA using astropy, scipy, matplotlib, and numpy.
- SOFIA FAQs: A website where I identified common questions and misconceptions and provided simple, yet detailed explanations not in observatory documentation.

Software Development for Research 🕠

- \circ The *DESK*: Independently led the development and publication of the first open-source python package to fit the light and colors of evolved stars with models to get meaningful properties.
- \circ The *BEAST*: Improved on testing and functionality of a large-scale open-source astropy-affiliated python package with a large team with different levels of coding experience.

PRESS

Sky at Night magazine interview about SOFIA New Zealand deployment NASA press release, SOFIA Watches a Binary Star System's Eclipse

AWARDED FELLOWSHIPS

2015 E. A. Milne Traveling fellowship (£ 2500) 2012 National Science Foundation Summer REU fellowship

ACADEMIC SERVICE

| Organized and gave the SOFIA New Zealand Lecture Series | July 2022 |
|---|---------------|
| SOFIA School Co-Chair | February 2022 |
| STScI postdoctoral representative | 2020 - 2022 |
| Bystander Intervention Workshop | March 2021 |
| DELVE conference SOC | February 2021 |
| Low-Density Universe Lunch Organizer | 2018 - 2019 |
| | |

TAC Panel Support: Hubble & SOFIA

Referee: Astrophysical Journal; Astronomy & Astrophysics

Links: ADS, ORCID, Google Scholar

REFEREED PUBLICATIONS

First-Authored Peer-Reviewed Publications:

- Goldman S. R. et al., 2022, ApJS, 259, 41
 A Census of Thermally-Pulsing AGB stars in the Andromeda Galaxy and a First Estimate of their Contribution to the Global Dust Budget
- 2. Goldman S. R., 2020, JOSS, 5(54), 2554 citations: 5 The Dusty Evolved Star Kit (DESK): A Python package for fitting the Spectral Energy Distribution of Evolved Stars. Journal of Open Source Software
- 3. Goldman S. R. et al., 2019, ApJ, 884, 152 AGB Stars in the Nearby Galaxy: Leo P
- 4. Goldman S. R. et al., 2019, ApJ, 877, 49 citations: 24
 An Infrared Census Of Dust In Nearby Galaxies With Spitzer (DUSTiNGS): V. The Periodluminosity Relation For Dusty Metal-poor AGB Stars
- 5. Goldman S. R. et al., 2018, MNRAS, 473, 3835 citations: 18 A dearth of OH/IR stars in the Small Magellanic Cloud
- 6. Goldman S. R. et al., 2017, MNRAS, 465, 403 citations: 116
 The wind speeds, dust content, and mass-loss rates of evolved AGB and RSG stars at varying metallicity

Co-Authored Peer-Reviewed Publications:

- 7. Mull et al. 2022, ApJ, 941, 206

 A Panchromatic Study of Massive Stars in the Extremely Metal-Poor Local Group Dwarf Galaxy
 Leo A
- 8. Ingallinera et al. 2022, MNRAS, 512, 21
 Evolutionary map of the Universe (EMU): 18-cm OH-maser discovery in ASKAP continuum images of the SCORPIO field
- 9. Sankrit et al. 2022, ApJ, 926, 177 SOFIA/FORCAST Monitoring of the Dust Emission from R Aqr: Start of the Eclipse
- 10. Scicluna et al. 2022, MNRAS, 512, 1091

 The Nearby Evolved Stars Survey II: Constructing a volume-limited sample and first results from the James Clerk Maxwell Telescope
- 11. Jones et al., 2021, MNRAS, 504, 565

 Infrared variable stars in the compact elliptical galaxy M32
- 12. Girardi et al., 2020, ApJ, 901, 19
 PHAT XX. AGB stars and other cool giants in M31 star clusters
- 13. Nanni A. et al., 2019, MNRAS, 487, 502

 The mass-loss, expansion velocities and dust production rates of carbon stars in the Magellanic Clouds

- Dharmawardena T. E. et al., 2019, MNRAS, 489, 3218
 The Nearby Evolved Stars Survey: I. JCMT/SCUBA-2 Sub-millimetre detection of the detached shell of U Antliae
- Karambelkar V. R. et al., 2019, ApJ, 877, 110
 SPIRITS Catalog of Infrared Variables: Identification of Extremely Luminous Long Period Variables
- Orosz G. et al., 2017, AJ, 153, 1190
 Astrometry of OH/IR stars using 1612 MHz hydroxyl masers. I. Annual parallaxes of WX Psc and OH138.0+7.2
- 17. Groenewegen M. A. T. et al., 2016, A&A, 596, A50

 The ALMA detection of CO rotational line emission in AGB stars in the Large Magellanic Cloud
- 18. McDonald I. et al., 2015, MNRAS, 453, 4324

 ALMA reveals sunburn: CO dissociation around AGB stars in the globular cluster 47 Tucanae

Other Publications:

- 19. Goldman et al. 2022, Research Notes of the AAS, 6, 159 Sudden Dimming of the Symbiotic Mira HM Sge
- 20. Goldman et al. 2022, AAS Meeting, 240 proceedings, 426.04

 A Census of Thermally-Pulsing AGB stars in the Andromeda Galaxy and a First Estimate of their Contribution to the Global Dust Budget
- 21. Sloan et al. 2021, AAS Meeting, 237 proceedings, 541.16 Spitzer's Last Look at the Small Magellanic Cloud.
- 22. Scicluna et al. 2020, arXiv:2002.03100 (Decadal white paper)

 Studies of Evolved Stars in the Next Decade: EAO Submillimetre Futures White Paper Series
- 23. Karambelkar et al. 2020, AAS Meeting, 235 proceedings, 335.04

 SPIRITS catalog of infrared variables: Identification of extremely luminous long period variables
- 24. Goldman S. R. and Boyer M. L., 2019, IAU Meeting 343 proceedings, 14(S343), 406-408 Infrared light curves of dusty & metal-poor AGB stars
- 25. Goldman S. R. and Boyer M. L., 2019, AAS Meeting 233 proceedings, 33.06 Infrared light curves of dusty & metal-poor AGB stars